Hello, and welcome to my talk.
大家好 欢迎来到我的演讲
In this presentation I'm going to talk about
在演讲中 我将为大家介绍
how Clipchamp has adopted WebCodecs
Clipchamp在过去12个月中
in the past 12 months, round about.
大体上是如何采用WebCodecs的
Clipchamp is an in browser video editor. slide-3
Clipchamp是一个浏览器中的视频编辑器 slide-3
At Clipchamp our mission is to empower anyone,
我们的使命是让任何人都能够
to tell stories worth sharing. slide-4
讲述值得分享的故事 slide-4
And what that looks like is we have built a fully
因此 我们在浏览器中打造了
in-browser video editor. slide-5
一个完整的视频编辑器 slide-5
And we firmly believed from the early days of when we
我们从公司成立早期就坚信
founded the company that only in-browser platforms offer
只有浏览器平台
the convenience of such a cloud service
才能兼具云服务的便利性
combined with the speed of a desktop application,
和桌面应用的处理速度
and we've used that in-browser paradigm. slide-6
我们也一直在使用这种浏览器模式 slide-6
For one, probably the most important reason is that
首先 可能最重要的原因是
caters for a great user experience.
这提供了优秀的用户体验
And the reason for that is video files are large. 18-p
而其原因是视频编辑的素材文件很大 18-p
It also comes with the fantastic advantage from a
从商业角度来看 它还有一项很棒的优势
commercial perspective that it has near zero runtime cost.
即它的运行成本几乎为零
The hardware has already been paid for. 21-p
硬件成本已经支付过了 21-p
And finally, there's also the aspect of privacy,
最后 还有隐私方面的问题
obviously very important in this day and age
隐私在这个时代显然非常重要
where everything you do not upload to a cloud service,
你并不会把所有信息上传到云服务中
but that stays on your devices is obviously
它们会只留在你的设备上
kind of subject to perfect privacy. slide-7
这显然是很好的隐私处理方式 slide-7
The browser remains a challenging platform, as you all know,
诚然 浏览器仍是一个具有挑战性的平台
especially when you do heavy lifting like
特别是当你在执行
video encoding or decoding. 29-p
像视频编解码这样的大型任务时 29-p
And that is obviously first and foremost resource allocation.
而首要的就是资源分配问题
Memory is scarce still. Performance is
内存仍然稀缺 性能也同样重要
equally important. Video encoding is expensive
如果你使用软件编码模式
if you use software encoding paradigm, as we,
视频编码成本会很高
for the longest time have done. Access to low-level hardware
就像我们在很长一段时间内所做的那样
capabilities, again, is limited.
而且对底层硬件能力的访问也有限
Yes, these days you do have WebAssembly SIMD and we've
没错 现在的确有了WebAssembly SIMD
made good use of that. You do have WebGL for a long time.
我们也利用了它 WebGL也存在很长时间了
WebGPU has just launched and thankfully,
WebGPU刚刚推出 值得庆幸的是
and obviously that's where WebCodecs fit in. 39-p
这显然是最适合WebCodecs发挥的地方 39-p
We now also have access to the circuitry that's devoted to
我们现在也可以使用专门用于硬件加速的
hardware accelerated video and audio decoding and encoding.
音视频编解码的逻辑单元
And that's fantastic for us. 42-p
这对我们来说非常好 42-p
The two aspects that I encircled
我在这里用紫色圈出的
in purple here, performance and access to
两个方面 即性能和
low level hardware capabilities,
对底层硬件能力的访问
are obviously the challenges that WebCodecs addresses slide-8
显然是WebCodecs要解决的挑战 slide-8
Talking about a lot of video processing pipelines
目前存在多种视频处理流程
specifically about probably the most challenging part
其中可能最具挑战性的部分
which is when you're exporting a video project that you've
就是当你导出你一直在编辑的视频项目时
been editing, where you put together various pieces of footage.
你会把各种视频片段放在一起
So that project which combines all of that,
因此 该项目将这些片段组合在一起
or can combine all of that, turn that into an MP4 file,
或者说能够组合在一起 输出为MP4文件
which you can then distribute around the web. slide-8
然后你就可以发布至网页 slide-8
That is quite an involved process. And again,
这是一个相当复杂的过程 同样
we run it all in the browser and currently
我们仍然是在浏览器中运行这一切
it's subdivided into three stages. 56-p
目前它被细分为三个阶段 56-p
Here we have the decoder which takes care of extracting
在这里 我们有一个解码器
a stream of, you know,
它负责从你的源素材中
kind of raw frames from your source footage
提取原始帧流
and then passed into the middle stage,
然后传到中间阶段
which we call the compositor that is where,
我们称之为合成器
all of those pieces of footage are combined,
在这里 所有这些片段被组合起来
effects are layered on top. And that one again,
效果会分层排在顶部 而这一阶段
produces a composed stream of raw frames,
又会产生一个由原始帧组成的流
which is then passed into the encoder,
然后传入编码器
which turns it into an MP4 file. 66-p
将其输出为一个MP4文件 66-p
We basically retrofitted WebCodecs into this architecture. slide-9
我们基本上把WebCodecs改造成这样的架构 slide-9
And the way we did that is we combined that
它将我刚才展示的FFmpeg的
WebAssembly build of FFmpeg that
WebAssembly构建
I was just showing you with the WebCodecs API
与WebCodecs API结合起来
and the way to do that is we created codec stubs, inside FFmpeg,
原理是在FFmpeg内部创建了编解码器存根
and what those codec stubs then do is they call out from
而这些编解码器存根的作用是
that WebAssembly build into JavaScript land. 73-p
将WebAssembly构建调用到JavaScript域 73-p
And that is basically to go through the WebCodecs API
这就是经历了WebCodecs API的整个生命周期
lifecycle, or it's lot better to say the VideoEncoder API
或者说是WebCodecs规范中的
inside of the WebCodecs specification.
VideoEncoder API更为准确
Initially, you initialize and configure your VideoEncoder
首先 显然你需要初始化和配置你的
instance, obviously. 78-p
VideoEncoder实例 78-p
And then you go through the process of pushing in the raw
然后你要经历推入原始帧的过程
frames and then pulling out the encoded chunks,
然后取出编码块
which are then put back to FFmpeg,
将其放回FFmpeg
which then puts them into the container format.
然后将其放入容器格式
And lastly, you close down and de-initialize
最后停用并反初始化
your VideoEncoder instance. slide-10
VideoEncoder实例 slide-10
Now that has worked really well for us,
这对我们来说是相当有效的做法
but it didn't come without some gotchas.
但它也存在着一些问题
And that's maybe the most interesting part of this talk. 87-p
这也许是本次演讲中最有趣的部分 87-p
And maybe then also,
也许还能
stimulate some discussions around what can be done
在面临同样挑战的人群中激起一些讨论
about that for others who have had the same challenges. 90-p
看看能否得出一些好的对策 90-p
What we had to do is create an artificial,
我们必须要做的是人工创建一个
pre-flight dry run of the video encoder using the same
视频编码器的预检模拟运行 使用相同的参数
parameters, same resolution, same everything,
相同的分辨率 相同的一切
just to generate that piece of extra data. 94-p
只是为了生成那块额外的数据 94-p
And I think in WebCodecs API
我记得在WebCodecs API术语中
parliance, it's called a description.
这块数据被称为“描述”
And it's basically for, if you know about H.264,
如果你了解H.264编码的话
they have these binary units in there,
其中有这些二进制单位
which are basically metadata, SPS/PPS, and that has to
基本上是储存SPS/PPS的元数据 它必须
be placed or has to be put back to FFmpeg,
被放到或者说必须被放回FFmpeg
such that it can be put in the container format at the
这样它就可以被放在容器格式的正确位置
right place. Now I leave it at that.
关于这个问题我就暂时先说到这里
But that has given us a bit of a bit of headache to,
但是为了解决这个问题
to get this right. 104-p
我们绞尽了脑汁 104-p
One concern, which has less to do with WebCodecs,
还有一个问题 与WebCodecs关系不大
but more with the fact that FFmpeg as such
主要是与FFmpeg有关
is obviously normally used as a command line tool,
因为FFmpeg通常作为命令行工具来使用
And that means it's typically a synchronous call stack and
这意味着它是一个典型的同步调用栈
that's inherently not a good fit for WebCodecs,
从本质上来说它并不适合WebCodecs
which is, like any browser,
因为任何浏览器
almost any browser API asynchronous.
几乎任何浏览器的API都是异步的
You have to break up the synchronous call stack for FFmpeg
你必须把FFmpeg的同步调用栈
into multiple asynchronous calls. slide-11
分解成多个异步调用 slide-11
And lastly, we have a bit of a wishlist.
最后 我们有一个小小的愿望清单
Obviously WebCodecs 1.0 or the current version of WebCodecs,
当前版本的WebCodecs 1.0
I should say, it's great.
显然是十分值得称赞的
A big thank you goes out to all the people that have pushed
非常感谢所有推动这一标准的人
for this standard, who have implemented it in browsers. 118-p
他们在浏览器中实施了这一标准 118-p
I can only imagine that it might've been a hard sell because like,
我能想象到这可能有点过了
you know, it's a very specialized capability.
因为它是一项非常专业的功能
Nevertheless, it's, you know,
尽管如此 就现在而言
kind of fantastic that this has happened. 122-p
它也是值得赞叹的 122-p
That being said, if you're hoping that
话虽如此 但我们还是希望
it doesn't remain this way, but that further
它不会固步自封 而是进一步
iterations on that standard.
对标准进行迭代更新
And there are a few things we are hoping for that would make
同时我们也有几点需求
our lives a little bit easier. 127-p
能让我们的工作更轻松一些 127-p
One thing we were struggling with, and where we again
有一个问题一直在困扰着我们
have only a crutch in place, there's not an active
我们目前也只是勉强解决了它
back pressure on the VideoEncoder object where
即在VideoEncoder对象上没有主动背压机制
the VideoEncoder object actively tells you
VideoEncoder对象应当能够主动提示你
to throttle the way you pass raw video frames,
对你传递原始视频帧的方式进行限流
and basically my buffers are all full.
提示你缓冲区基本已经满了
So it'd be good to see some sort of event coming out of
因此 要是VideoEncoder对象能提供一个事件
video encoder object that actively tells people
主动提醒我们 说“先停下 等我指令”
"stop until I tell you otherwise". 136-p
那就更好了 136-p
Another concern is right now,
另一个问题是现在
the way to configure video encoders
配置视频编码器的方式
is largely through the bitrate.
主要是通过比特率
And that's okay for many typical workloads,
这对许多典型的工作负载来说可以接受的
think about streaming scenarios and so forth,
想想流媒体场景等等
but in our case for a video editor,
但在我们的用例中
you are probably a bit more focused on,
对于视频编辑来说
you are probably a bit more obsessed about quality,
可能会更关注质量
visual quality that is.
这里说的的是图像质量
It would be good to have some sort of semantic
如果有某种语义上的
quality tuning knob,
质量调整旋钮就好了
which is more like an abstract parameter which just says,
这更像是一个抽象的参数 范围从0到1
from zero to one, one means perfect quality, zero means crap quality
1代表最佳质量 0代表最低质量
and anything in between,
以及两者范围之内的数值
but that gives you like a bit of a more objective means
但这更像是一种客观的手段
to control the quality other than the bitrate. 154-p
来取代比特率对质量进行控制 154-p
Obviously HDR matters more and more,
显然 HDR越来越重要
as more displays are being in use, on phones its already commonplace,
越来越多的显示器和手机都在使用HDR
TV is pretty much the same,
电视也差不多
PC monitors maybe not quite as much yet,
桌面显示器也许还没有那么普遍
but it would be good to see that being supported
但如果看到WebCodecs也能支持HDR
by WebCodecs as well. 160-p
那就更好了 160-p
HEVC decoding,
HEVC解码
and I know there's an entire discussion around IP and patent
我知道存在知识产权和专利责任的问题
liability and so forth, but pretty much if WebCodecs
但如果WebCodecs能够接入
could tap into any codec that is installed on the device,
设备上安装的任何编解码器
even if it's selective, like if on some devices,
即使它是选择性的 比如某些设备
HEVC is not supported, fine,
不支持HEVC编码也没关系
and we have to offer a fallback in some sort of software
我们必须在某种软件服务编码中
service side encoding,
提供一个备选方案
but it would be good if at least the codecs that are
但如果安装的编解码器
installed would be kind of funneled through and exposed
至少能够通过WebCodecs的接入实现支持
through WebCodecs. 171-p
那就更好了 171-p
And unfortunately there's certain well-known companies that
可惜的是 有一些知名的公司
push for HEVC despite the difficult IP situation.
不顾知识产权的困阻 努力推动HEVC的发展
So that's something that's an audience we want to cater for. 175-p
这也是我们想要迎合用户的需求 175-p
And I mentioned that synchronous flavor of the WebCodecs
我也提了 WebWorker内部的
API inside workers would be useful as well. 177-p
WebCodecs API的同步调用风格也会很有用 177-p
I didn't include the demuxing and muxing part. I mean,
我没有把与复用/解复用相关的放进来
we support these through FFmpeg. And I wouldn't claim
是因为我们可以通过FFmpeg支持这些功能
this goes with our challenges probably for new adopters of
这对我们来并不是什么挑战 可能对于
the WebCodecs API is one of the greatest concerns. 181-p
WebCodecs API的早期采用者 这是最大的问题之一 181-p
In general, WebCodecs as such doesn't offer anything
一般来说 WebCodecs本身并不提供任何
by way of kind of parsing a video file.
解析视频文件的方法
So the demuxing part, or producing an MP4 file. 185-p
以及解复用的部分 输出一个MP4文件 185-p
I don't know what the solution to that might be.
我不确定这方面有什么可能的解决方案
There's obviously a lot of complexity in this part.
但显然这部分有很多复杂的问题
And FFmpeg already does all of that.
而FFmpeg已经支持了所有这些
So that's why I didn't include it.
所以我没有把它放进来
I'm not sure if it's a good idea to include this into
我不确定将其纳入WebCodecs是否是好事
WebCodecs, because this is a bit of a different concern,
因为这个问题有别于其他的问题
even though pretty much anyone using WebCodecs would
即便几乎所有使用WebCodecs的人
probably have to deal with it one way or another. slide-12
都可能不得不以某种方式解决它 slide-12
And that concludes my talk.
我的演讲到此结束
Thank you. And I'm free for questions.
谢谢 欢迎提问